Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're talking about where people come from or nationalities.
我是Catherine，今天我们讨论的是人们来自哪里，或者说国籍。
That's right.
没错。
Many people come from many different countries just like our listeners and there are specific
很多人来自许多不同的国家，就像我们的听众一样，而且有一些特定的
words or adjectives and nouns to describe people.
词语、形容词和名词来描述这些人。
Like for example, somebody who is from China.
比如，有人来自中国。
A Chinese person.
一个中国人。
That's right.
没错。
So in your case, Marco, you are an Ecuadorian.
所以就拿你来说，Marco，你是一个厄瓜多尔人。
That's right.
没错。
So that means I come from the country Ecuador.
这意味着我来自厄瓜多尔这个国家。
I, on the other hand, am an American.
而我呢，是一个美国人。
I come from America.
我来自美国。
That's right.
没错。
So we have a lot of these examples.
所以我们有很多这样的例子。
Why don't we jump into the dialogue.
我们不如直接进入对话吧。
Let's see where all of the people from this international class are from and we'll be
让我们看看这个国际班里的所有人都来自哪里，然后我们会
back to talk about it.
回来讨论。
Hey how was your first day of class?
嘿，你第一天上课怎么样？
I'm a level two and I'm loving my class this semester.
我是二级班，这学期我很喜欢我的课。
It's great being in a class of international students.
在一个国际学生班里真是太棒了。
Mine was okay except that no one in my class speaks English.
我的课还行，只是班上没人说英语。
I guess it will force me to converse in Chinese more in class so at least I should improve
我想这会逼我在课上多说中文，所以至少这学期我应该能
a lot this semester.
进步很多。
That's both fortunate and unfortunate.
这既是幸运也是不幸。
It's the United Nations in my class.
我们班就像联合国一样。
We have people from all over the world.
我们有来自世界各地的人。
There are three Germans, a Pole, a Scot, two French, an American, a Brazilian, a Chilean,
有三个德国人、一个波兰人、一个苏格兰人、两个法国人、一个美国人、一个巴西人、一个智利人、
a New Zealander, though he prefers to call himself a Kiwi.
一个新西兰人，不过他更喜欢称自己为Kiwi。
Who else do we have?
还有谁呢？
Oh we have a Moroccan, a Tagolese, a Pakistani, and two Indonesians.
哦，我们有一个摩洛哥人、一个多哥人、一个巴基斯坦人和两个印度尼西亚人。
That's quite the array of nationalities.
真是各种各样的国籍啊。
Everyone in my class is from Asia except me.
我们班上除了我，所有人都来自亚洲。
There are a few South Koreans, several Japanese, Malaysian, Thai, Singaporean, Filipino, Kazakhstani,
有几个韩国人、几个日本人、马来西亚人、泰国人、新加坡人、菲律宾人、哈萨克斯坦人，
and one Russian.
还有一个俄罗斯人。
Well I think you're pretty lucky actually.
嗯，我觉得你其实挺幸运的。
You have the opportunity to learn so much about Asian culture.
你有机会学到很多关于亚洲文化的东西。
I guess so but I think it's going to be hard to relate to my classmates especially with
我想是吧，但我觉得和同学们相处会很难，尤其是
the language barrier.
语言障碍。
I think I might change classes.
我可能会换班。
Don't stay the course.
别放弃，坚持下去。
Your spoken Chinese will be eternally grateful.
你的中文口语会因此受益匪浅的。
I bet you it will even surpass mine with all that practice.
我敢打赌，经过这么多练习，它甚至会超过我的中文。
I highly doubt it.
我非常怀疑。
Your girlfriend is Chinese.
你女朋友是中国人啊。
Well there is that, yes.
嗯，这倒是，没错。
So the student jokes that their class is kind of like the United Nations.
所以那个学生开玩笑说他们的班有点像联合国。
So it does sound like it.
听起来确实如此。
We have so many different nationalities that we're going to look at them in two groups
我们有这么多不同的国籍，今天我们会把它们分成两组
today.
来看。
But the United Nations as you know is a political group that has people from all over the world
但联合国，如你所知，是一个政治组织，有来自世界各地的人
who make decisions about politics and the environment, things like that.
来决策政治和环境之类的事情。
That's right.
没错。
So why don't we take a look at these nationalities now on Language Takeaway.
那么，我们现在就在“语言小贴士”环节来看看这些国籍吧。
Language Takeaway.
语言小贴士。
The first few are from Europe.
前几个来自欧洲。
So these are some European nationalities.
所以这些是一些欧洲国籍。
We've got German.
我们有德国人。
Where is a German from?
德国人来自哪里？
A German is from Germany.
德国人来自德国。
Okay, so next to Germany we have another country, Poland.
好的，那么德国旁边是另一个国家，波兰。
What do we call a person from Poland?
我们怎么称呼来自波兰的人？
You call that person a Pole.
你称那个人为波兰人。
So is this for a woman and a man or is this just one gender?
这是指女性和男性，还是只指一种性别？
Yeah, it's for both.
是的，两者都适用。
Okay, so Pole.
好的，所以是波兰人。
Yeah, a girl that's from Poland would be also a Pole.
是的，来自波兰的女孩也是波兰人。
Now someone that comes from Scotland on the other hand.
而来自苏格兰的人呢？
That would be a Scot or if it's a man, a Scotsman.
那会是苏格兰人，如果是男性，就是Scotsman。
Scotsman, okay.
苏格兰人，好的。
Now this is interesting because we are mentioning the nouns of these nationalities like for
这很有趣，因为我们提到了这些国籍的名词，比如
example German.
德国人。
Now when we took a look at Pole from Poland, what would be the adjective?
当我们看来自波兰的波兰人时，形容词是什么？
Do I say I am Pole?
我可以说“我是波兰人”吗？
I am Polish.
我是波兰的。
Or if you want to use the noun, I am a Pole.
或者如果你想用名词，我是波兰人。
But the adjective can be used for things as well.
但形容词也可以用于事物。
I love to eat Polish sausages.
我喜欢吃波兰香肠。
Or for example or something from Scotland, you can say I love Scottish whiskey.
或者比如来自苏格兰的东西，你可以说我喜欢苏格兰威士忌。
Or I love Scottish kilts, those skirts.
或者我喜欢苏格兰短裙，那些裙子。
Alright, so that's the adjective.
好了，所以那是形容词。
But in the case of France, the country France, we have to say as a noun, he is a Frenchman.
但就法国这个国家而言，作为名词，我们必须说他是法国人。
Okay, and if it's a woman, a Frenchwoman.
好的，如果是女性，就是法国女人。
That's right or in the case of an adjective, I love to eat French bread.
没错，或者作为形容词，我喜欢吃法式面包。
Okay.
好的。
Now moving on to South America, we took a look at a Brazilian and a Chilean.
现在转到南美洲，我们看了看巴西人和智利人。
Okay, so Brazil, Brazilian.
好的，所以巴西，巴西人。
In this country, there are many Brazilians.
在这个国家，有很多巴西人。
And Chile or Chile as many Americans say, has people called Chileans.
而智利，或者很多美国人说的Chile，那里的人叫智利人。
Some people say Chilean.
有些人说Chilean。
So I don't know, I guess the accent varies a little bit.
所以我不知道，我猜口音有点不同。
Now why don't we move back to the other side of the world.
现在我们为什么不回到世界的另一边呢。
We have a New Zealander.
我们有新西兰人。
Alright, so many of you have heard of Australia.
好的，你们很多人听说过澳大利亚。
Maybe New Zealand is not as famous.
也许新西兰没那么出名。
It's a small country near Australia.
它是一个靠近澳大利亚的小国家。
And the people who come from there are called New Zealanders.
来自那里的人被称为新西兰人。
It's very hard to say those sometimes, especially when we have to use the adjective New Zealand.
有时候很难说这些词，尤其是当我们必须用形容词“新西兰”的时候。
That's right.
没错。
So the student said he prefers to call himself a Kiwi.
所以那个学生说他更喜欢称自己为几维鸟。
Alright, so Kiwi was a special kind of bird that could only be found in New Zealand.
好的，几维鸟是一种只能在新西兰找到的特殊鸟类。
And so this became a very popular symbol for New Zealand.
所以这成了新西兰非常流行的象征。
And now people from New Zealand call themselves Kiwis.
现在来自新西兰的人称自己为几维鸟人。
So I could say I have many Kiwi friends.
所以我可以说我有很多几维鸟朋友。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, Kiwis.
好的，几维鸟人。
So now if we go to the African continent, we have Moroccan and Togolese.
所以现在如果我们去非洲大陆，我们有摩洛哥人和多哥人。
So Morocco is in North Africa and a person who comes from there is Moroccan.
所以摩洛哥在北非，来自那里的人是摩洛哥人。
You can also say I like to eat Moroccan food, which is very popular.
你也可以说我喜欢吃摩洛哥菜，这很受欢迎。
But when we talk about the country Togo, what do we call a person from that country?
但当我们谈论多哥这个国家时，我们怎么称呼来自那个国家的人？
Togolese.
多哥人。
So it's Togo.
所以是多哥。
That's the way you pronounce it.
那是你发音的方式。
Because if you look at it, I would say Togo.
因为如果你看这个词，我会说多哥。
Right?
对吧？
But it's not Togo.
但并不是多哥。
It's Togo.
而是多哥。
Or as my French-speaking friends would say, Togo.
或者像我说法语的朋友会说的，多哥。
That's right.
没错。
Alright, so that's our first set of nationalities.
好了，这是我们的第一组国籍。
Let's listen to today's dialogue one more time and we'll be back in a moment to discuss
让我们再听一遍今天的对话，稍后回来讨论
the other nationalities.
其他国籍。
Hey, how was your first day of class?
嘿，你第一天上课怎么样？
I'm a level two and I'm loving my class this semester.
我是二级班，这学期我很喜欢我的课。
It's great being in a class of international students.
在一个国际学生班级里真是太棒了。
Mine was okay, except that no one in my class speaks English.
我的还行，只是班上没人说英语。
I guess it will force me to converse in Chinese more in class, so at least I should improve
我想这会迫使我在课堂上多说中文，所以至少这学期我应该能进步
a lot this semester.
很多。
That's both fortunate and unfortunate.
这既幸运又不幸。
It's the United Nations in my class.
我们班就像联合国一样。
We have people from all over the world.
我们有来自世界各地的人。
There are three Germans, a Pole, a Scot, two French, an American, a Brazilian, a Chilean,
有三个德国人，一个波兰人，一个苏格兰人，两个法国人，一个美国人，一个巴西人，一个智利人，
a New Zealander, though he prefers to call himself a Kiwi.
一个新西兰人，虽然他更喜欢称自己为几维鸟人。
Who else do we have?
还有谁？
Oh, we have a Moroccan, a Togolese, a Pakistani, and two Indonesians.
哦，我们有一个摩洛哥人，一个多哥人，一个巴基斯坦人，和两个印度尼西亚人。
That's quite the array of nationalities.
真是各种各样的国籍。
Everyone in my class is from Asia, except me.
我们班上除了我，所有人都来自亚洲。
There are a few South Koreans, several Japanese, Malaysian, Thai, Singaporean, Filipino, Kazakhstani,
有几个韩国人，几个日本人，马来西亚人，泰国人，新加坡人，菲律宾人，哈萨克斯坦人，
and one Russian.
还有一个俄罗斯人。
Well, I think you're pretty lucky, actually.
嗯，我觉得你其实挺幸运的。
You have the opportunity to learn so much about Asian culture.
你有机会学到很多关于亚洲文化的东西。
I guess so, but I think it's going to be hard to relate to my classmates, especially with
我想是吧，但我觉得很难和同学相处，尤其是
the language barrier.
有语言障碍。
I think I might change classes.
我想我可能会换班。
Don't!
别换！
Stay the course.
坚持下去。
Your Chinese will be eternally grateful.
你的中文会永远感激你的。
I bet you it will even surpass mine with all that practice.
我打赌经过这么多练习，它甚至会超过我的中文。
I highly doubt it.
我非常怀疑。
Your girlfriend is Chinese.
你女朋友是中国人。
Well, there is that, yes.
嗯，确实如此，是的。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now we have more nationalities prepared for you.
所以现在我们为你们准备了更多国籍。
So let's take a look at those now on Language Takeaway Part 2.
让我们在语言要点第二部分看看这些。
Language Takeaway We're in Asia for this part of today's lesson,
语言要点 今天课程的这一部分我们在亚洲，
so we're going to start with a country called Pakistan.
所以我们要从一个叫巴基斯坦的国家开始。
What do we call the people from Pakistan?
我们怎么称呼来自巴基斯坦的人？
We say they are Pakistani.
我们说他们是巴基斯坦人。
Okay, so in Chicago, for example, there are many Pakistanis.
好的，比如在芝加哥，就有很多巴基斯坦人。
Okay, and moving on to Southeast Asia, we have Indonesians.
好的，接下来到东南亚，我们有印度尼西亚人。
All right, Indonesia is the country, and people who come from there are Indonesian.
没错，印度尼西亚是国家，来自那里的人就是印度尼西亚人。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
Now if we go back to the north part of Asia, we have South Koreans.
现在如果我们回到亚洲北部，我们有韩国人。
So we have North and South Korea on our maps.
所以地图上有北韩和南韩。
A person from North Korea is North Korean, and a person from South Korea is South Korean.
来自北韩的人是北韩人，来自南韩的人是南韩人。
It's kind of like that same structure, American, Brazilian, Korean.
这有点像同样的结构，美国人、巴西人、韩国人。
Very good.
非常好。
And moving to the island of Japan, we have Japanese.
然后到日本这个岛国，我们有日本人。
So this is an adjective.
所以这是一个形容词。
We're talking about a Japanese person.
我们在谈论一个日本人。
He is Japanese.
他是日本人。
Or we can also talk about the food, like sushi is Japanese food.
或者我们也可以谈论食物，比如寿司是日本食物。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, moving back to Southeast Asia again, we have Malaysia.
好的，再回到东南亚，我们有马来西亚。
So people from Malaysia are called Malaysian.
所以来自马来西亚的人被称为马来西亚人。
Okay, again with this pattern, Malaysian, Korean.
好的，又是这个模式，马来西亚人、韩国人。
That's right.
没错。
And I think you say Malaysian food or you say Malay?
我想你是说马来西亚食物还是马来食物？
I've heard some people say Malay.
我听过有些人说马来。
I've said Malaysian food generally, but Malay I think is one of the languages, and I think
我一般说马来西亚食物，但马来我认为是一种语言，而且也是
it's an ethnic group as well, so you can have Malay people in Singapore, for example.
一个族群，所以你可以有马来人，比如在新加坡。
Okay.
好的。
And actually we have Thai people and Singaporeans.
实际上我们还有泰国人和新加坡人。
So we have two countries there, Thailand and Singapore.
所以那里有两个国家，泰国和新加坡。
So Thai is the adjective to describe things that come from Thailand.
所以泰是形容词，用来描述来自泰国的事物。
It's kind of unusual.
这有点不寻常。
It doesn't fit that pattern that I mentioned, but it's a very important one to remember
它不符合我提到的那个模式，但如果你喜欢吃这个国家的食物，泰国菜，
if you like to eat food from this country, Thai food.
这是一个很重要的要记住的词。
Yeah, excellent food.
是啊，美味的食物。
And Singaporean food is also pretty good, and people from Singapore are also called
新加坡食物也相当不错，来自新加坡的人也被称为
Singaporean.
新加坡人。
Here we've got a very tricky one.
这里有一个非常棘手的词。
We've got the country, the Philippines.
我们有国家，菲律宾。
What do you call a person from the Philippines?
你叫来自菲律宾的人什么？
So the Philippines is actually spelled P-H-I, like Philippines, right?
所以菲律宾实际上拼写是P-H-I，像菲律宾，对吧？
But if somebody is from the Philippines, we say Filipino with an F.
但如果有人来自菲律宾，我们说菲律宾人，用F开头。
All right, Filipino.
好的，菲律宾人。
This is interesting, especially for people who are native Spanish speakers because the
这很有趣，特别是对于母语是西班牙语的人来说，因为
Philippines was a Spanish colony for a very long time, and so you might hear someone refer
菲律宾曾经是西班牙殖民地很长时间，所以你可能会听到有人自称
to himself as a Filipino.
为菲律宾人。
He's a man.
他是男人。
Or if she is a woman, a Filipina.
或者如果她是女人，菲律宾女人。
So this is very similar to the Spanish structure of having a gender on the end of the word.
所以这非常类似于西班牙语结构，词尾有性别。
That's right.
没错。
And well, now we're moving on to Kazakhstan and Russia.
好了，现在我们转到哈萨克斯坦和俄罗斯。
We have people that are from Kazakhstan and Russia, and we say they are Kazakhstani.
我们有来自哈萨克斯坦和俄罗斯的人，我们说他们是哈萨克斯坦人。
So this is very common in that part of the world to end the adjective in an I, like Afghanistan,
所以在世界那个地区，以I结尾的形容词很常见，比如阿富汗，
Afghani, Pakistan, Pakistani, Kazakhstan, Kazakhstani.
阿富汗人，巴基斯坦，巴基斯坦人，哈萨克斯坦，哈萨克斯坦人。
And so these are the stans, the former USSR.
所以这些是斯坦国，前苏联国家。
So this is a very important structure to remember, but Russia is pretty easy.
所以这是一个很重要的要记住的结构，但俄罗斯很简单。
Yeah, people from Russia, you say they are Russian or you have Russian food.
是啊，来自俄罗斯的人，你说他们是俄罗斯人，或者你有俄罗斯食物。
I love Russian food.
我喜欢俄罗斯食物。
All right, so we have a lot of different nationalities there.
好的，所以我们有很多不同的国籍。
And obviously we didn't cover all of them.
显然我们没有涵盖所有。
I think, I don't know, maybe 200 nationalities.
我想，我不知道，大概200个国籍。
So why don't we listen to the dialogue again, and we'll be back to talk a little bit more
所以我们为什么不再次听对话，然后我们会回来多聊一点
about this really interesting topic.
这个非常有趣的话题。
Hey, how was your first day of class?
嘿，你第一天上课怎么样？
I'm a level two and I'm loving my class this semester.
我是二级班，这学期我很喜欢我的课。
It's great being in a class of international students.
在国际学生班里上课很棒。
Mine was okay, except that no one in my class speaks English.
我的课还行，只是班上没人说英语。
I guess it will force me to converse in Chinese more in class.
我想这会逼我在课堂上多用中文交流。
So at least I should improve a lot this semester.
所以至少这学期我应该进步很多。
That's both fortunate and unfortunate.
这既幸运又不幸。
It's the United Nations in my class.
我班上就像联合国一样。
We have people from all over the world.
我们有来自世界各地的人。
There are three Germans, a Pole, a Scot, two French, an American, a Brazilian, a Chilean,
有三个德国人，一个波兰人，一个苏格兰人，两个法国人，一个美国人，一个巴西人，一个智利人，
a New Zealander, though he prefers to call himself a Kiwi.
一个新西兰人，虽然他更喜欢称自己为几维鸟。
Who else do we have?
我们还有谁？
Oh, we have a Moroccan, a Tagolese, a Pakistani, and two Indonesians.
哦，我们有一个摩洛哥人，一个多哥人，一个巴基斯坦人，和两个印度尼西亚人。
That's quite the array of nationalities.
真是各种各样的国籍。
Everyone in my class is from Asia, except me.
我班上除了我，所有人都是亚洲人。
There are a few South Koreans, several Japanese, Malaysian, Thai, Singaporean, Filipino, Kazakhstani,
有几个韩国人，几个日本人，马来西亚人，泰国人，新加坡人，菲律宾人，哈萨克斯坦人，
and one Russian.
和一个俄罗斯人。
Well, I think you're pretty lucky, actually.
嗯，我觉得你其实挺幸运的。
You have the opportunity to learn so much about Asian culture.
你有机会学到很多关于亚洲文化的东西。
I guess so, but I think it's going to be hard to relate to my classmates, especially with
我想是吧，但我觉得很难和同学建立联系，特别是
the language barrier.
有语言障碍。
I think I might change classes.
我想我可能要换班了。
Don't!
别换！
Stay the course.
坚持下去。
Your spoken Chinese will be eternally grateful.
你的中文口语会因此感激不尽的。
I bet you it will even surpass mine with all that practice.
我敢打赌，经过这么多练习，它甚至会超过我的水平。
I highly doubt it.
我对此深表怀疑。
Your girlfriend is Chinese.
你女朋友是中国人。
Well, there is that, yes.
嗯，确实如此。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So talking about nationalities, I think there's one that we didn't mention that's very, very
说到国籍，我觉得有一个我们没提到，而且非常非常
popular.
流行的。
People from Ireland.
来自爱尔兰的人。
Okay, so people from Ireland are called Irish.
好的，所以来自爱尔兰的人被称为Irish。
Irish.
Irish。
The Irish or Irishmen.
爱尔兰人或爱尔兰男人。
This is a similar structure to a lot of those countries in Northern Europe like Sweden and
这和很多北欧国家，比如瑞典和
Finland.
芬兰，的结构类似。
That's right.
没错。
So somebody from Sweden would be called Swedish.
所以来自瑞典的人被称为Swedish。
Yes, or a Swede is the noun.
是的，或者Swede是名词形式。
So I love to eat Swedish food like salmon.
所以我喜欢吃瑞典食物，比如三文鱼。
But a similar structure applies to Finland.
但类似的结构也适用于芬兰。
In Finland, they're very famous for their Finnish bread.
在芬兰，他们的芬兰面包非常有名。
Finnish.
Finnish。
So that's the way that you say Finnish with double N, right?
所以这就是你读Finnish的方式，双N，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
It's not like I finished my homework.
它不像“我完成了作业”里的finished。
It's like F-I-N-N-I-S-H.
它是F-I-N-N-I-S-H。
Finnish.
Finnish。
And now, what about people from Denmark?
那么，来自丹麦的人呢？
They are Danish.
他们是Danish。
Danish.
Danish。
And what about people from Norway?
那来自挪威的人呢？
They are Norwegian.
他们是Norwegian。
So that's one that does not fit the pattern.
所以这是一个不符合规律的情况。
And this is a very interesting one that also doesn't fit the pattern at all.
还有一个非常有趣的，也完全不符合规律。
People from Holland.
来自荷兰的人。
Okay, so Holland as a country has two names.
好的，所以荷兰这个国家有两个名字。
We sometimes say Holland.
我们有时说Holland。
We sometimes say the Netherlands.
我们有时说the Netherlands。
But a person who comes from Holland is called Dutch.
但来自荷兰的人被称为Dutch。
He is Dutch.
他是Dutch。
That's right.
没错。
So it doesn't have to do with neither Holland, you don't say a Hollander, or Netherlands,
所以它既和Holland无关，你不会说Hollander，也和Netherlands无关，
you don't say Netherlander.
你不会说Netherlander。
It's Dutch.
它是Dutch。
Dutch.
Dutch。
And you'll also read this on like cookie tins.
你也会在饼干罐上看到这个。
You know, boxes for cookies, Dutch style cookies.
你知道，装饼干的盒子，荷兰式饼干。
That's right.
没错。
All right, so that's a very important one when it comes to food.
好的，所以在食物方面，这是一个非常重要的词。
But we're very curious to hear about where you come from.
但我们非常好奇你来自哪里。
You should try some of the new vocabulary words that we have introduced here.
你应该试试我们这里介绍的一些新词汇。
Talk about your friends or your family.
聊聊你的朋友或家人。
But also, tell us if we didn't include your nationality.
另外，如果我们没有提到你的国籍，也请告诉我们。
That's right.
没错。
All right, so we'll see you guys there.
好的，那我们就在那里见。
EnglishPod.com.
EnglishPod.com。
Enjoy your meal!
请享用你的餐点！